<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in his Majesties Chappel at Whitehall on the eighth of February, 1684/5, being the Sunday after the death of His late Sacred Majesty, King Charles the Second of blessed memory by Thomas Horne ...</title>
            <author>Horne, Thomas, 1610-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4564</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13470193</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13470193</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99680</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44508)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99680)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 790:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in his Majesties Chappel at Whitehall on the eighth of February, 1684/5, being the Sunday after the death of His late Sacred Majesty, King Charles the Second of blessed memory by Thomas Horne ...</title>
                  <author>Horne, Thomas, 1610-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Horne ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A sermon preached at Whitehall.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Thessalonians, 1st, V, 19 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99680:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in His <hi>Majeſties Chappel</hi> AT WHITEHALL, ON The Eighth of <hi>February</hi> 1684/5.</p>
            <p>Being the <hi>Sunday</hi> after the Death of His late Sacred Majeſty King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second of Bleſſed Memory.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Horne,</hi> Fellow of <hi>Eaton</hi> Colledge, And Chaplain to His Late Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Horne,</hi> at the <hi>South Entrance</hi> of the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>MDCLXXXV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:99680:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99680:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Theſſ. 5.19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Quench not the Spirit.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is well known with what vehemence this Text has been urged againſt the uſe of <hi>Liturgies;</hi> and it has been made as manifeſt by Learned men, with how little juſtice it has been objected. So that it would ſeem frivolous to meddle with it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more; but that the Objections riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, after one would think they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated: And the Principles are as active, as if their Arguments were invincible. Wherefore ſince there is no end of objecting, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable (I hope) for us at leaſt to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Queſtion over again, if it be but to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99680:3"/>ſhew that we are neither aſhamed of <hi>Our Reaſons,</hi> nor afraid of <hi>Theirs.</hi> And this I intend to do fairly, without any heat of Controverſie; endeavouring rather to lay, than raiſe the duſt that in the heat of Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes blinds the eyes of men, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the native force and evidence of truth. Though it be hard to forbear ſpeaking warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to a Cavil which reproaches all our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and blaſts all thoſe Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions you put up this laſt Week in behalf of our <hi>dying Soveraign,</hi> the fervency of which I know not where to parallel. For if this Objection be true; in all thoſe <hi>ſtrong Cries and Supplications,</hi> you took more than ordinary pains to <hi>Quench the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queſtion I intend to examine is, Whether Forms of Prayer <hi>quench</hi> (or <hi>ſtint) the Spirit,</hi> as they uſe to ſpeak? Which Queſtion, I will firſt ſtate plainly, and then propoſe the method of ſearching into it.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion will be clearly ſtated, by ſhewing, firſt, what is meant by <hi>Forms of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99680:3"/>Prayer;</hi> Secondly, What it is to <hi>ſtint the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>Forms of Prayer,</hi> is meant either the determining before we pray, what <hi>things</hi> ſhall be the <hi>matter</hi> of our Prayer, leaving the words to be moulded <hi>ex tempore;</hi> or elſe the determining beforehand both what things to pray for, and alſo in what expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. The former of theſe we may call a <hi>Form of Matter</hi> onely; the latter, a <hi>Form of Matter and Words</hi> too: and both theſe may be either mutable, or fixt as a conſtant Rule of Worſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By <hi>ſtinting the Spirit</hi> muſt be meant either the hindering or quenching of the bleſſed Influence of the Holy Spirit <hi>of God</hi> upon our Souls in prayer; or elſe the infee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the vigour of Devotion in the ſpirit <hi>of man;</hi> the depreſſing our affections in their flight to the throne of Grace; the ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the pious zeal of the Heart, the extinguiſhing that holy fire of the Altar in which the Sacrifice of Prayer ſhould aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:99680:4"/>
            <p>The ſtate of the Queſtion therefore is this; Whether a <hi>Form of Matter</hi> onely, or a <hi>Form of Matter and Words</hi> too, hinder ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Influence of the Spirit of God, or the Soul of man in prayer.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe when we look upon things in groſs, we ſee them confuſedly, and are apt to ſhuffle Truth and Falſhood together; therefore I will reſolve Prayer into its ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt Principles, that we may judge more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly of the Queſtion before us, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this following method.</p>
            <p>Firſt, All publick Prayer in the Church is made up of the Prayers of ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; therefore we may conſider of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in one man, and ſee what quenches the Spirit in him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Prayers of the Church are made up of variety of <hi>matter;</hi> as Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of ſins, Praiſes and Thankſgivings, and of many Spplications for Spiritual and Temporal good things: wherefore we may ſelect one out of one of theſe ſorts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that diſtinctly. Suppoſe any man
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99680:4"/>would requeſt of our heavenly Father ſome one ſignal bleſſing; as, that God would <hi>ſave the King,</hi> (which was your mournful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and muſt ſtill be your dutiful Prayer.) But becauſe that would provoke a paſſionate ſorrow which bleeds yet, and I would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeak to your Judgment, I will ſuppoſe rather that a man intends to beg of God that gift of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> which is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the 11th of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> v. 13. which we do pray for in the Lords Prayer, and frequently in the reſt of our Prayers.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as in other Prayer, ſo in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſupplication for Gods Spirit, we may conſider the outward prayer of Words, and the inward prayer of the Heart, from whence the outward ought to flow.</p>
            <p>The buſineſs is now drawn into a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row compaſs; and the careful conſidering of it thus, will be (I hope) a clue to lead us into a true judgment of the whole Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:99680:5"/>
            <p>Firſt then, this inward Prayer of the Heart is the Soul and Life of all Prayer, which God eſpecially requires, and therefore chiefly regards, and favourably accepts: Without this, the outward pouring forth of words is a noiſome carkaſs, whether we uſe a form of words, or new conceived fluen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Words were made for man; not to help God to underſtand our meaning, who looks into a deſire, and ſearches thought; who takes notice of the firſt ſprings of the motion of our mind towards him. This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward deſire muſt be in all, whether publick or private Prayer, or nothing is done. Prayer may be without words, and words may be without prayer: for <hi>that</hi> is the very eſſence, <hi>theſe</hi> are not. And from hence it follows, firſt, that words conceived <hi>extempore</hi> cannot be an ingredient neceſſary to make our Prayers accepted of God. Secondly, that the uſeful and neceſſary help or gift of the Spirit in Prayer, is to be placed in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Prayer of the Heart, and not in expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of words, where the life of Prayer is not. And this one conſideration might be enough
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99680:5"/>to end all diſpute about <hi>extempore</hi> words of Prayer.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If a man addreſs himſelf to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of God this bleſſing of his Spirit, though he ſupplicate without uttering one word, yet here is a form (a form of matter) and that as narrow as can be: for his Spirit can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be more ſtinted, than when it petitions for one thing. If therefore this ſo narrow a form does not quench the Spirit of God, nor hinder the flight of his Prayer to the Throne of Grace, nor obſtruct its entrance, nor make the mercy of God turn away his ear from attending to his ſuit; what larger form can do it? And to ſatisfie us that this does in no wiſe hinder his Prayer, we may conſider further,</p>
            <p>That in the third place, every ſober Chriſtian, and man of ſenſe, will readily grant that he will pray more heartily and acceptably to God when he begs this grace of the Holy Spirit, if he go beforehand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Cloſet and meditate on his own ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold frailties, and conſequently his great
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99680:6"/>need of this grace. No man can deny that he ſhould fix and prepare his heart, by the conſideration of Gods fatherly goodneſs and bounty, eſpecially of his promiſe of <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Holy Spirit to them that ask it;</hi> and all in order to the ſtrengthning his Faith, and dependance on God, and for the increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his humility, and the ſetling his good purpoſes and attention. Certainly this ſhould be the work of our retirement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we pray, without which our thoughts will be apt to play and wander at the time of Prayer, and the pantings of the heart will be more languid.</p>
            <p>But all this preparation bounds the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of a man to that particular matter which he is to ſue for, and this binding is the very thing which makes it a form; ſo that the more a man premeditates, the more is his Spirit bounded or ſtinted to his particular form of matter which he prays for; and ſo the more he is ſtinted, the better he prays.</p>
            <p>For this meditation reſtrains the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Underſtanding, and by that means quickens his deſire; that is, it puts a ſtop
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99680:6"/>to wandring thought, and fixes it upon that one bleſſing he would requeſt, and gathers together the ſcattered motions of the Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and determines all his earneſt deſire to that one point; which reſtraint inflames Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Zeal, and gives it a greater force: As winds are ſtrongeſt in their narroweſt paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as a vaſt Ocean when it rolls all one way, and beats with its whole weight upon a ſtreight Channel; that very ſtinting of it makes the Waves rage, and multiplies the ſwiftneſs and vehemence of their motion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond imagination, that it forces its way with irreſiſtible violence; but when once it has paſſed from thence into a wide ſpace, and gained the room it ſtruggled for, there where the way is open and free, all its vigour is loſt in it ſelf, and becomes a pacifick Sea.</p>
            <p>We may take notice by the way, that it is advantageous (which ſome complain of) for the <hi>Liturgy</hi> to be divided into ſeveral diſtinct Prayers, that we may requeſt more earneſtly while we determine our Souls to ſingle petitions; whereas if all the Prayers were made into one long Oration, we could not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99680:7"/>ſo eaſily diſcern where one Requeſt ends and another begins; ſo that the intention of our minds would be loſt, and the undeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined vigour of deſire be becalmed as in a wide Sea. The ſum of this is, that Preme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation on one ſingle form, does not hinder but help the Spirit of man.</p>
            <p>It is hard to conceive how that which is ſo uſeful, ſo neceſſary a preparative to ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Devotion, ſhould any wiſe hinder the Spirit of God on the heart of man in ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; yet leſt I ſhould ſeem to ſhift away from the buſineſs, I will conſider this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly. If a man pray for the conduct of Gods gracious Spirit, what operations of the Spirit are needful in this Supplication? what are neceſſary to attain the end Prayer, <hi>i. e.</hi> acceptance with God? I conceive that if he have a love of God and Goodneſs, a belief of that Promiſe made by Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. a fervent deſire of the grace of God, humility, and a ſerious purpoſe of obeying its direction, his Prayer will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. Now ſerious premeditation, ſuch as I have deſcribed, is the very exerciſe of all theſe. Conſideration of the fatherly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99680:7"/>goodneſs and promiſe of God made by Chriſt, is the very exerciſe of Faith in him, and a proper incitement to a greater love of him. The weighing with himſelf the great and manifold imperfections of his corrupt nature, and therefore his great want of the continual aids of the Holy Spirit, kindles ardent deſire, and increaſes humility; which is alſo furthered by reflecting on his own unworthineſs, compared with the unlimited bounty, and unmerited goodneſs of God; and all together are ſtrong motives to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter purpoſes and ſtronger reſolutions. Is it poſſible that the exerciſe of Faith, Love, Zeal, Humility, and Reſolution, ſhould hinder the Spirits working theſe very things? when they are the <hi>preparations of the heart,</hi> which, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.1. <hi>are from the Lord.</hi> One might as well ſay, that Pride, neglect of God, or Infidelity, further the operations of the Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>Again, if after this preparation of heart, a man addreſs himſelf to the ſame Prayer in that very devout poſture of mind in which his meditation left him, aſſuredly the Spirit of God will perfect what it ſelf began, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99680:8"/>aſſiſt him more yet in that Prayer to which it prepared him. The Royal Prophet ſays, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17. that <hi>the Lord hears the deſire of the humble, he will prepare their heart, and will cauſe his ear to hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, ſince both the firſt thoughts in the preparing meditation, and the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſires in act of Prayer, are from God, it follows, that he who conſiders beforehand, has a portion of the Spirits help double to what the <hi>extempore</hi> man has, who knows not beforehand what he ſhall pray, but invents his petition in the moment when he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents it. So far is a prepared form of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from hindring the good effects of Gods Spirit on the mind of man, that it is a great furtherance. And from hence we gain al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a new Argument for the former Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>i. e.</hi> that it does not hinder the ferven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of mans Spirit: For that which furthers the effects of Gods Spirit, cannot hinder ours in the leaſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let us go on with our ſingle Form, and ſuppoſe that this Man reſolves with himſelf never to ceaſe from begging the promiſed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99680:8"/>Spirit of God, but to wreſtle daily for this great bleſſing; here it becomes a ſtated or praeſcribed Form to him, as much as if it were appointed by Authority, and he were reſolved to obey it: and this is our caſe in praying by a <hi>Liturgie.</hi> And in this caſe neither is the Spirit of God quenched, nor the mans own Spirit hindred: Not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, becauſe he obeys that command of our Saviour, in the 18 St. <hi>Luke, v.</hi> 1. to <hi>pray always and not to faint, i. e.</hi> not to give over the ſame requeſt, as Chriſt explains himſelf in the words immediately following, by that Parable of the importunate Widow, who continued to ſollicite the unjuſt judge with the ſame ſuit, till ſhe had obtained her deſire; and therefore if he ſhould not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat that Prayer, it would be a neglect of a plain duty; which ſinful neglect muſt really hinder and quench the Spirit. Nor can the mans own Spirit be ſaid to be hindred, unleſs we will blaſphemouſly affirm, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour has given ſuch a command about our Prayer, as hinders our Soul from praying a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we ſhould.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99680:9"/>
            <p>Now if we apply what has been ſaid hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto of one mans ſingle petition, to all the Prayers of a Congregation, it is manifeſt, that ſince the moſt limited Form does not any wiſe quench the Spirit of God, or the Soul of Man; ſince if it does ſtint our mind, it does it to advantage, by ſtopping only the looſe roving of invention, whetting thereby the ſerious deſire of the Soul; our large and comprehenſive Forms cannot be a hindrance to Prayer by any narrowneſs that is in them.</p>
            <p>The truth is, we continually offend our good God, frequently in the commiſſion of the ſame ſins, and in the omiſſion of the ſame duties; and they muſt be confeſſed: moſt mercies we receive every day, and every moment, and they deſerve inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant thanks: the infinite and peerleſs perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of God, are <hi>the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever,</hi> and therefore the ſame praiſe endureth for ever: our needs are for the moſt part the ſame, eſpecially our Spiritual wants, which require the moſt intenſive fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency; therefore the chief matter of Prayer is ſuch as muſt not be changed. There is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99680:9"/>no ſuch place in the ſubſtance of Prayer for the new invention of men, as ſome are apt to conceive. Shall we invent ſins <hi>extempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> to confeſs before God? we commit too many, and it will take up time enough to conſider well of them. Can we invent At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes in God to magnifie? they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable. Can we invent mercies to thank him for beſides what we have received? that imagination is vain, and unworthy of God; let us offer our thanks with gratitude for what we have received. Or ſhould we invent new Topicks of Bleſſings to ask of him? let us firſt conſider what we do need, and requeſt thoſe things ſeriouſly.</p>
            <p>There is <hi>one thing neceſſary,</hi> which we are every day to ſeek: we always want the grace of God, and muſt always pray for it: we need the heavenly food, and muſt daily pray that God would <hi>give us ever more this bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I acknowledge that if a man ſhould pray daily for one particular matter onely, ſo as to exclude others that are neceſſary; or if our publick Prayers omitted ſome important requeſt, and we were hindred from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99680:10"/>our neceſſary Petitions; then the Spirit would be ſtreightned. But what is wanting in the <hi>Liturgie</hi> that it is fit to beg of God? what would any of us want if God ſhould grant us all that is contained in the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> in the full extent of it? or what want is there which we cannot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs our ſelves to God for in a ſhort Ejacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, in the time of publick Prayer, or elſe in private, and ſo compleat the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed defect of the <hi>Liturgie?</hi> This we can do if we are in earneſt, and therefore no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can hinder us, but onely our ſelves. When there is a prepared Heart, there is nothing without can put a ſtop to the inward operations of mans Spirit; nothing can obſtruct the courſe of the thoughts, or block up the Will from deſiring; no power on earth can ſtop the freedom of its courſe; no obſtacle in Nature can reach it.</p>
            <p>I have ſpoken as fully as is fit to the form of Matter, not wholly omitting to ſpeak of Words; and much more need not be ſaid of them, but that the people of our Nation have an unaccountable fondneſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99680:10"/>for the <hi>extempore</hi> effuſion of the words of Prayer; though they love not that phraſe <hi>extempore</hi> Prayer, but chooſe to call it <hi>conceived</hi> Prayer. Their opinion of it is ſtrange, becauſe all men muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the Life of Prayer is in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the inward man, and that words are but the outward dreſs of Prayer, and that the Spirit and Life of Prayer cannot be in that which is but the outward part; yet when the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England</hi> uſe the Forms preſcribed (ſuppoſe in the <hi>Viſitation of the Sick</hi>) many of the common people think that they have little or nothing of the Spirit of Prayer in them, becauſe they do not invent a new Prayer; and no good is done, unleſs ſome private perſon comes and prays for ſome time with a multitude of ready utterance: then they think there is the Spirit of Prayer; which ſhews that they are verily perſwaded that that there is more of the Spirit in Words than really there is.</p>
            <p>And the name they give to this <hi>extempore</hi> utterance is as ſtrange: for no reaſon can be given why that which is not thought of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99680:11"/>before, but invented in the moment of ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance, ſhould be called <hi>conceived Prayer,</hi> to diſtinguiſh it from other Prayer: for certainly that which is premeditated and thought of frequently before, and alſo in the time of Prayer, is conceived too; and the more it is thought of, the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            <p>However, let us conſider whether a Form of Words hinders either the Work of the Spirit of God, or the Spirit of man in Prayer. That they do not hinder the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, I argue firſt from hence, That it cannot be proved that the Spirit of God does always give new expreſſions of Prayer. Suppoſe in the firſt place, that the Spirit did once give a man the very Words of Prayer, and he ſhould conſtantly uſe thoſe Words, he would pray <hi>as the Spirit gave him utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;</hi> and yet this would be a Form of Words. And ſuch a Spiritual Form of Words is the <hi>Lord's Prayer.</hi> Now there is no juſt reaſon to think the Spirit ſhould continually change thoſe firſt Words for new: for as the Apoſtle reaſons, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.7. concerning the Covenants, <hi>If the first Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99680:11"/>had been faultleſs, there had been no need of the ſecond;</hi> ſo there is no need of new Words unleſs the firſt had been faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And beſides this, the rules which are given in Holy Writ, for the manner of framing our Words, argue that the Spirit did not intend alway to indite the Words, but leave them to man: as that Rule which <hi>Solomon</hi> gave, Eccleſ. 5.2. <hi>Be not raſh with thy mouth, and let not thine heart be haſty to utter any thing before God: for God is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and thou upon earth; therefore let thy words be few.</hi> And our Saviours rule, 6 Matth. 7. <hi>Not to uſe vain repetitions as the Heathen,</hi> or <hi>to think we ſhall be heard for much ſpeaking:</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9. it is manifeſt that he purpoſely gave his prayer in few words, to prevent the uſing many words in prayer: <hi>Be not ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore like unto them,</hi> i. e. in multiplying words; <hi>for your Father knoweth what things ye have need of, before ye ask him. After this manner therefore pray ye: Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. That is, in this ſhort way, <hi>therefore</hi> that ye may avoid much ſpeaking. Another rule the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Solomon</hi> affords, in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6. throughout, whoſe prayer is made up chiefly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99680:12"/>of the words of Gods promiſes to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. What need of giving us rules for our Words, if the Spirit gives the Words? or of what uſe are the Rules when given, if we are not to do it?</p>
            <p>Secondly, I argue from the general opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe who love <hi>extempore</hi> prayer, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Spirit of God; for they gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſay, that the work of the Spirit is after an irreſiſtable manner upon the Elect, and therefore it cannot be hindred there; and as for the Reprobate, if any work of the Spirit be hindred in them, it can do no hurt.</p>
            <p>Let us ſee in the next place, whether Forms of Words hinder the Spirit of man.</p>
            <p>There are but theſe three uſes of Words that I can think of in Prayer; Firſt, to expreſs the matter or thing which we beg of God. Secondly, to expreſs our deſire of that which we pray for, <hi>i. e.</hi> the earneſtneſs or height of our deſire. Thirdly, to kindle affection in them that hear us. I can name no more, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be by Words to win upon God, and perſwade him to hearken and grant; which I hope no man dares to think.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:99680:12"/>
            <p n="1">1. As to the firſt, I cannot ſee how Forms of Words ſhould hinder our Spirit, but by ſtinting the mind to the things which they ſignifie. Now if a man were to pray that Prayer, which I have ſo often ſpoken of, for the promiſed Spirit of God; let the Words be varied an hundred ways, whether <hi>extempore</hi> or by meditation, yet ſtill (if the expreſſions are not fooliſh, but fit to ſignifie the matter) they all mean the ſame thing; and ſo the mind is as much tyed to the ſame ſubject, as if there were but one ſort of expreſſion: and therefore if a Form of Matter does not hinder us, neither does a Form of Words.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But I verily believe that it is not the Matter ſo much, as the intenſe <hi>ardor</hi> of their <hi>deſire,</hi> which the men that uſe <hi>extempore</hi> prayer would fain expreſs by Words; which fruitleſs endeavour I confeſs a <hi>Liturgie</hi> hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders indeed. They would ſhew either to God or the People how much they are in earneſt; how vehemently they <hi>pant after the living God;</hi> they would find words to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99680:13"/>ſignifie how much they <hi>hunger and thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter righteouſneſs.</hi> But there are no living words that can fully expreſs the degrees of affection, or the heights of deſire, any more than there are colours to paint the ſwiftneſs of an arrow: therefore though they labour for Words, and ſtretch invention, yet the <hi>unalterable groans</hi> cannot be uttered. But becauſe they think they may come ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing nearer, as the invention grows warm, they try it over again, and ſtrive to find new ways; and this delightful play of the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they think to be like <hi>Job</hi>'s <hi>pleading</hi> with the Almighty, and <hi>Jacobs wreſtling</hi> for the bleſſing; and that this can come from nothing but the Spirit, and that therefore Forms quench the Spirit.</p>
            <p>But this proceeds from an opinion, that there is more of the Spirit of Prayer in Words, than there is really; and from a perſwaſion that there is more need of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing in Words the fervour of our Zeal, than in truth there is: for beſides that the thing cannot be done, yet if it could, there is no need of wording our affection to God, who knows our needs, and the ſincerity of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99680:13"/>our deſire: and to men we ſhould not be over-deſirous to expreſs it, becauſe it lies open ſo much to oſtentation; it proceeds alſo from a forgetfulneſs of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s advice, that <hi>God is in heaven, and we are upon earth, and therefore our words ſhould be few,</hi> Eccleſ. 5.2.</p>
            <p>A third uſe of Words is to raiſe our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which <hi>extempore</hi> Prayer pretends much to; and therefore it is commonly objected, that the conſtant uſe of a <hi>Liturgy</hi> makes the people pray lazily. It is true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that <hi>extempore</hi> Prayer has raiſed in the people an affection to the men of that way, and a ſcorn of Forms. It is true, that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of paſſionate words does pleaſe the ears of men; But that it has made the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple more Serious and truely Devout, is not ſo true: there is nothing which unconſidered words can do, which ſerious conſideration beforehand of the Majeſty of the Great God, and of the weighty things we are to requeſt, will not do a great deal better, and without the danger of ſudden invention; for <hi>in the multitude of words there is vanity,</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99680:14"/>one mean expreſſion or fooliſh word is apt to ſpoil more ſerious devotion in the hearer, than can be mended again in a great while: and it is this vanity of words which Forms are deſigned to hinder.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is objected that a <hi>Liturgy</hi> makes men pray lazily, it ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered whether ſomething elſe has not deadned the Devotion beforehand, when the <hi>Liturgy</hi> is accuſed of it.</p>
            <p>If I approach before God with a ſenſeleſs mind, with deſires after wickedneſs, or bent wholly on this world, this does <hi>quench the Spirit of God,</hi> and take away the life of Prayer. For how can we pray for the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Spirit of God, while we have ſome ſin reigning in us which will not let us yield to the conduct of his Grace? if I come with an unprepared careleſs heart, not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering either the great Majeſty of God, or the Bleſſings I ſhould pray for, I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy murdered my own Devotion, and my Prayer will be formal whether I pray <hi>extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> or by a Form. If we regard not the mercies of God, how can we give thanks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right?
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99680:14"/>if we account lightly of the Offences we have committed againſt the Lord of the whole Earth, or intend to commit them again, or care not if we do, all our Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions will be onely in words. If a man come with a prejudice againſt a Form, or a ſcorn of our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> the ardency of Prayer is already extinguiſhed. So that many times the Devotion is ſlain beforehand, and the <hi>Liturgy</hi> is accuſed of it, becauſe it does not raiſe the dead.</p>
            <p>Let men bring hither a prepared and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiced heart, let them lay aſide the love of words, and ſcorn of our Prayers, let them come full of reverence to God and truſt in him, with ſerious thankfulneſs, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency, contrition, and Religious reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and then ſee whether a Form can hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them.</p>
            <p>Another frequent Pretence or Objection there is, that the Forms preſcribed, tye us up ſo that we cannot enlarge our Spirit accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the extraordinary caſes that may happen. Suppoſe a man is under any Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual deſertion, or heavy affliction, or fallen into ſome heinous ſin, or has received ſome
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99680:15"/>freſh comfort, or any great bleſſing; here are not Prayers enough for theſe emergent occaſions, and this ſeems to hinder our Spirit. This I call a pretence; for commonly it is ſo: becauſe extraordinary caſes are not a reaſon againſt the ordinary uſe of <hi>Liturgies.</hi> As to the Objection in thoſe extraordinary caſes, I ſay, that beſides the proviſion made in the <hi>Liturgie</hi> for many caſes, beſides the extraordinary Forms put forth by Authority for publick caſes; this does not hinder our Prayer, <hi>i. e.</hi> the earneſt requeſt of the Soul, but only the expreſſing our caſe particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. But neither Forms of Prayer, nor <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore</hi> conceived Prayer, can particularly expreſs every caſe that may happen to every private man; neither is there ſo much need of reporting our caſes particularly before God, for he knows whereof we have need, and what we do but deſire. When Chriſt bids us pray thus for the Neceſſaries of this life, <hi>Give us this day our daily bread;</hi> do you think our Father knows not that we want raiment and health too? or that he will forget to give them, becauſe they are not expreſly mentioned? this were to think the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99680:15"/>or bounty of God are ſtraight and narrow like ours.</p>
            <p>If it be meant that a Form of Words cannot comprehend our particular caſe, or that our Spirit is ſo detained thereby, that we cannot enlarge our ſelves ſo as to reach our caſe; this is a very groſs miſtake, for want of conſidering the general and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive words in which our Common Prayers are expreſt.</p>
            <p>I will explain my ſelf by one inſtance for many, in thoſe words of Confeſſion, <hi>We have done thoſe things which we ought not to have done,</hi> &amp;c. Suppoſe that one man of the Congregation has fallen into ſome great ſins, and another has been guilty of others, and ſo on: After we have conſidered every one privately thoſe particular ſins in which each one has offended God, we can all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burden our Conſciences before God, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to him our ſeveral offences, though we uſe the ſame words; becauſe they are large and general, and ſo compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all our particular ſins. Apply the ſame to Thankſgiving, to Praiſe, and Supplication, and the caſe will be very clear; for theſe are
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99680:16"/>the great parts of our Prayer. But this previous conſideration is the great labour of real Prayer, which moſt men love to eſcape.</p>
            <p>Whatever extraordinary caſe happens to any of us, ſtill preparation is needful before we approach unto God in Prayer. And for this reaſon the conſtant uſe of <hi>extempore</hi> Prayer in publick, does and muſt hinder the real Spirit of Prayer, becauſe it hinders the preparation of heart to all that ſhall be pray'd for. For if the Miniſter change e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very time his Words and Matter, or if he reſerves to himſelf whether he will change, or how much, it is utterly impoſſible for the Auditors any more than to gueſs what he will ſay. And how then can they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare their hearts for the particular things which he ſhall chance to pray for.</p>
            <p>I wiſh thoſe who ſcorn our Forms, would conſider, where the life of Prayer is, and contend earneſtly for that. It cannot be in Words, and therefore they ſhould place no more in them than they are capable of. Prayer is not an exerciſe for mens parts, not to ſhew ready invention, or elocution, (much leſs vainity) but humble deſire, and Faith in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99680:16"/>God: God is not taken either with ſounds, or outward geſtures, that pleaſe the eyes and ears of men; but with ſincerity and uprightneſs, which man cannot diſcern. Theſe may be where there are no variety of delightful Words, and paſſionate exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and the petitions are then accepted. On the other ſide, all the outward ſhews of zeal may be without the life of Prayer; and then the Words beat the air, and return emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and God is offended too. The abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of melting words may come from the heart; but they may <hi>not come</hi> from thence; and what man knows the heart of another? And if all do come from the real zeal of him who ſpeaks; yet it is your faith and ferven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, not meerly his, that will procure you a bleſſing from God. Wherefore we ſhould labour to wean our ſelves from this love of the new words of Prayer, and ſtrive more earneſtly for the inward and Spiritual part of Prayer, which none can deprieve us of; in words we may be deceived, and in all that is outward; in this we cannot. The Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans prayer had but few words, and that was accepted; the Phariſee prayed thrice as long, and returned empty.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:99680:17"/>
            <p>Why ſhould any man preſume to offer to God any thing unconſidered: <hi>the words of raſhneſs, and the froth of the lip!</hi> why of all perſons ſhould any man chooſe to trifle with the Majeſty of the Living God? But when through a haſt to utter any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, men have ſpoke unadviſedly with the Tongue, and have not conſidered that they do evil, it is adding mad preſumption to the ſay, <hi>the Lord has done it;</hi> or that his wiſe Spirit has put it into their heart to utter vanity.</p>
            <p>And let us who are ſatisfied that Forms do not <hi>quench the Spirit,</hi> take care of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to God, that we do not quench the Spirit of Prayer by negligent approach to him. Since we who pray by a <hi>Liturgie,</hi> have this advantage of thoſe who do not, that we know beforehand what Petitions we are to put up, that we can conſider and weigh them all, which they cannot; let us not looſe the advantage, and offer <hi>extemporary</hi> deſires be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. Let private meditation prepare us for our publick Prayer, that our thoughts being fixed beforehand, and our fervent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire kindled, we may enter into the Houſe of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99680:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>God ſo full of awful reverence, that there may be no room for levity and rambling imaginations: that irreverence and careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs being baniſhed away, we may have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do but to confeſs with good purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and pray earneſtly, and give thanks with joy and gratitude, and be more ready to hear than to offer the Sacrifice of Fools; that we may ſay with the Royal Prophet, <hi>My heart is fixed O God, my heart is fixed, I will ſing and give praiſe,</hi> and ſo of the other parts of our Worſhip. And then I doubt not, but the experience of upright men would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide this queſtion in favour of <hi>Liturgies,</hi> as effectual as any thing, unleſs the publick <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempore</hi> Prayers had been printed, as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer is; which would have extinguiſht all their glory, as the Sepulchral Lamps go out when they are expoſed to the Light.</p>
            <p>They who never have been uſed to Forms, or come not with an unprejudiced intent to pray heartily by them, can be no judges whether Forms hinder the Spirit; whether are they judges who ſeem to like the Common Prayer, but bring no Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to it. I appeal to the ſerious devout
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99680:18"/>perſons of this place, who continually attend upon Prayer; whoſe zealous devotion is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable and exemplary, who are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore competent judges. Did you ever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach with a Religious ſenſe of the Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of God, with a real deſire to requeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bleſſing of him, and were hindred by the <hi>Liturgie?</hi> have you not rather found that every expreſſion was weighty, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to your conſiderate zeal?</p>
            <p>I appeal to your Devotion this laſt week, ſo fervent and unwearied. Did not your hearts burn within you at every interceſſion you ſo earneſtly put up for our late Dread Soveraign? you ſeemed to pray as if you were in all his weakneſs, and felt all his pains, from the firſt aſtoniſhing ſtroak to his laſt gaſp. You were with him in all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, the fearful and deſpairing changes: you ſeemed to groan with the Agonies of his Death: you carried your Tears and Prayers, hour after hour, from the Cloſet to this place with ſome impatience, waiting for the next opportunity of imploring God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for him, and rejoycing when it was ſome; as if every one were mourning over
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99680:18"/>their <hi>firſt born.</hi> And when the laſt ſad news came, you ſubmitted to Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and rejoyced in a peaceable Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as much as paſſionate grief could give leave.</p>
            <p>You have really ſet your ſelves a pattern of fervent Prayer for your whole life. If ever you would requeſt of God any great bleſſing, remember how you prayed this week; and let your own example ſtir up your Devotion for the future.</p>
            <p>And take care that you do not <hi>quench the Spirit,</hi> by a perſwaſion that God hearkned not to you, becauſe he granted not that deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red life. For your dutiful and Loyal Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is yet acceptable to God, which is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable end of Prayer. We are taught to cloſe our daily Prayers with this ſubmiſſion to his wiſdom and goodneſs, <hi>Fulfil now O Lord the deſires and petitions of thy ſervants as may be moſt expedient for them.</hi> And if we pray with Faith in him, we ought to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that what he does is <hi>moſt expedient for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:99680:19"/>
            <p>Wherefore turn now the force of your Loyal Devotion, to thanks for our Gracious Soveraign, and Prayers for Gods bleſſing on him, for a Juſt and Wiſe, a long and peaceable Reign.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
